So, welcome to another session, so in this session we will discuss different system which
will be actually presented in the corporate environment.
And in the previous section we have discussed about the ways a model and a few network
concepts.
So, in the next section we are going to discuss about the different system that has been
used in the network.
So, first of all, so when we coming up to the different system in a network, so the firewall
will be the first thing that will coming into the into our mind, so we are going to discuss
about the firewall first.
So, let us say, so firewall is basically a security device, so either it will be like a hardware
or and it will be like a software for a combination of both.
So, sometime in some corporate environment the firewall is based on hardware, there is a
48 firewall, Cisco firewall and a lot of firewalls are there, so sometime we are using
the software for that example the Windows firewall and it will be a combination of both.
So, hardware under a solar system software, the main purpose of the firewall is like monitoring
the inbound and the outbound traffic.
So, let us consider here is our router and inside the router, so there is firewall inside
it.
So, after the firewall many devices has been connected under the firewall, so every device
is under the firewall it will send the traffic, it will send the traffic to the firewall,
then the firewall to router and the router to the internal, this is the scenario of the
firewall how our corporate environment will operate. So, in firewall there is a two thing
or there is an inbound rule and another one is a outbound rule. So, inbound rule is basically
we will see a diagram for that, so it is basically here is an attacker, so you can see
the inbound rule from the attacker machine to the corporate environment, so it is like, so
from internet to the router and router to firewall and firewall to the device. So, this
rule is called as inbound some incoming calls and some traffic are sending from devices
to firewall, firewall to router and router to internet. So, we will call this as a outbound
traffic, basically firewall will monitor this inbound and outbound traffic and if the traffic
was malicious, it will block that traffic, if the traffic was good it will allow that
traffic, based on the rules. So, firewall have some set of rules or policies, so it will
decide whether the packet was malicious or the packet was sending is malicious or packet
was receiving was good. So, basically it will monitor these two things, for other packets
are sending from the machine and what are the packets are receiving from the internet.
Based on the rule it will take a decision, so let we will see other features of the firewall
here and it is a best access control, if you want to block some devices from accessing
the internet, for example, so here is a device, so we are going to block this device
to access to the internet, so we can configure the device IP in a firewall and this firewall
will not send any traffic outside of the network, if it will block here. So, this is
a best access control mechanism and we have a packet filtering, so we can filter whatever
packets need to send to the internet and we can block based on that, based on the rule
it will act. So, it has a best VPN support, so VPN is used for connecting securely to
a remote network and it has a VPN filtering also, so if you want to block a pornography
or some adult flame, you can configure the same things in a firewall, it will automatically
block that websites. So, the firewall will be like this, if there is any unwanted connection
was coming, it will block here and the perimeter traffic only, it will be allowed inside
to the network. So, the inbound and outbound will be acts like this, the red column
is like a attacker traffic, so it was blocked and the good traffic was coming from the
server, so it has been allowed, so in the outbound packets, so inside one of the machine,
the proper environment, one of the machine was connecting with the malicious traffic, so
outbound packets that it has been blocked. So, it will be act like that, so next mechanism
we are going to see the IPS as well as the IDS, so IPS stand for the intrusion detection
system, sorry, IDS stand for intrusion detection system and IPS stand for an intrusion
prevention system, both of the technologies are used to detect and prevent the threats,
ok. So, this both are in the first method, we can discuss about the IDS, so IDS is also
like a firewall, it will monitor and analyze the network traffic, but the only difference,
it will not react, so let us see with the practical explanation with the diagram, so here
you have a router and inside the router you have placed IP IDS, ok. So, let us consider
some bad traffic was coming from here to here, and it was reaching to the machine, ok,
so it is a bad traffic, some bad traffic and the IDS will only detect that traffic, ok.
So, it will not prevent that, it will not block that, it only detect that, ok. So, after
detecting it will send alert to a administrator, ok, so it will send alert like some malicious
traffic has been detected, so it will send alert like this, ok. So, but the threats will
be allowed to the machine, ok. It will not block, it will just detect that, ok. So, if
you, so that is why we are saying the IPS, sorry, the IDS is a passive tool, IPS is active
tool, ok. Let us say the IPS here, so here we have an IPS intrusion prevention system
and the same like some bad traffic is reaching to IPS, and here is our machine. So,
it will detect that, and it will stop that, it will block that, ok. So, it will block,
it will respond, so response is like I need to block or I need to do something, ok. That
is a response, so it will block that, so we are calling this tool as an active tool, ok.
So, active and IDS is a passive, let us go to our presentation here, ok. So, let us jump
on to here, we will see the, we will already saw the thing, how it will be hacked. So,
the key difference between the IDS and IPS us, in IDS it will be one detecting and alerting
the threats, but IPS it will detect and prevent the threat. So, the response mode will
be the only alert, so that we are saying it is a passive, so but it will block the traffic,
so that we are saying it is an active, ok. So, the placement it will be placed outside
of the main firewall, so it is like the, so if there is a modem or router and the IDS
will be here, after IDS there is a firewall and IPS, so the structure will be like this,
ok. So, it will be placed outside of the firewall, so in line with the firewall, does
not affect network traffic, but it will affect the network, but we as it will block the
traffic, ok. So, alerts to administrators, but it will not give any alerts to the administrators,
ok. So, here is a diagram representation of IPS and IDS, so hope you enjoyed this video
and we will continue our different mechanism, network calls in our next video, see you
you guys, bye bye.